<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! trunk/opendj3/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2012 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<glossary xml:id='glossary'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>OpenDJ Glossary</title>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Abandon operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP operation to stop processing of a request in progress, after
   which the directory server drops the connection without a reply to the
   client application.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Access control</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Control to grant or to deny access to a resource.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="access-control-instruction">
  <glossterm>Access control instruction (ACI)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Instruction added as a directory entry attribute for fine-grained
   control over what a given user or group member is authorized to do in terms
   of LDAP operations and access to user data.</para>
   <para>ACIs are implemented independently from privileges, which apply to
   administrative operations.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="privilege" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Access control list (ACL)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An access control list connects a user or group of users to one or
   more security entitlements. For example, users in group "sales" are granted
   the entitlement "read-only" to some financial data.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm><filename>access</filename> log</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Directory server log tracing the operations the server processes
   including timestamps, connection information, and information about the
   operation itself.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Account lockout</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>The act of making an account temporarily or permanently inactive
   after successive authentication failures.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Active user</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A user that has the ability to authenticate and use the services,
   having valid credentials.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Add operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP operation to add a new entry or entries to the directory.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Anonymous</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A user that does not need to authenticate, and is unknown to the
   system.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Anonymous bind</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A bind operation using simple authentication with an empty DN and an
   empty password, allowing "anonymous" access such as reading public
   information.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="approximate-index">
  <glossterm>Approximate index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Index is used to match values that "sound like" those provided in the
   filter.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Attribute</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Properties of a directory entry, stored as one or more key-value pairs.
   Typical examples include the common name (<literal>cn</literal>) to store
   the user's full name and variations of the name, user ID
   (<literal>uid</literal>) to store a unique identifier for the entry, and
   <literal>mail</literal> to store email addresses.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm><filename>audit</filename> log</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Type of access log that dumps changes in LDIF.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Authentication</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>The process of verifying who is requesting access to a resource; the
   act of confirming the identity of a principal.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Authorization</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>The process of determining whether access should be granted to an
   individual based on information about that individual; the act of
   determining whether to grant or to deny a principal access to a
   resource.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Backend</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Repository that a directory server can access to store data. Different
   implementations with different capabilities exist.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Binary copy</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Binary backup archive of one directory server that can be restored on
   another directory server.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Bind operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP authentication operation to determine the client's identity in
   LDAP terms, the identity which is later used by the server to authorize (or
   not) access to directory data that the client wants to lookup or
   change.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Collective attribute</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A standard mechanism for defining attributes that appear on all the
   entries in a particular subtree.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Compare operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP operation to compare a specified attribute value with the value
   stored on an entry in the directory.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Control</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Information added to an LDAP message to further specify how an LDAP
   operation should be processed. OpenDJ supports many LDAP controls.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Database cache</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Memory space set aside to hold database content.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm><filename>debug</filename> log</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Directory server log tracing details needed to troubleshoot a problem
   in the server.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Delete operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP operation to remove an existing entry or entries from the
   directory.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="directory">
  <glossterm>Directory</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A directory is a network service which lists participants in the
   network such as users, computers, printers, and groups. The directory
   provides a convenient, centralized, and robust mechanism for publishing and
   consuming information about network participants.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Directory hierarchy</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A directory can be organized into a hierarchy in order to make it
   easier to browse or manage. Directory hierarchies normally represent
   something in the physical world, such as organizational hierarchies or
   physical locations. For example, the top level of a directory may represent
   a company, the next level down divisions, the next level down departments,
   and so on. Alternately, the top level may represent the world, the next
   level down countries, next states or provinces, next cities, and so
   on.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="directory-manager">
  <glossterm>Directory manager</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Default Root DN who has privileges to do full administration of the
   OpenDJ server, including bypassing access control evaluation, changing
   access controls, and changing administrative privileges.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="root-dn" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Directory object</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A directory object is an item in a directory. Example objects include
   users, user groups, computers and more. Objects may be organized into a
   hierarchy and contain identifying attributes.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="entry" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Directory server</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Server application for centralizing information about network participants.
   A highly available directory service consists of multiple directory servers
   configured to replicate directory data.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="directory" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="replication" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Directory Services Markup Language (DSML)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Standard language to access directory services using XML. DMSL v1
   defined an XML mapping of LDAP objects, while DSMLv2 maps the LDAP Protocol
   and data model to XML.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Distinguished name (DN)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Fully qualified name for a directory entry, such as
   <literal>uid=bjensen,ou=People,dc=example,dc=com</literal>, built by
   concatenating the entry RDN (<literal>uid=bjensen</literal>) with the DN of
   the parent entry (<literal>ou=People,dc=example,dc=com</literal>).</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Dynamic group</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Group that specifies members using LDAP URLs.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="entry">
  <glossterm>Entry</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>As generic and hierarchical data stores, directories always contain
   different kinds of entries, either nodes (or containers) or leaf entries. An
   entry is an object in the directory, defined by one of more object classes
   and their related attributes. At startup, OpenDJ reports the number of entries
   contained in each suffix.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Entry cache</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Memory space set aside to hold frequently-accessed, large entries,
   such as static groups.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="equality-index">
  <glossterm>Equality index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Index used to match values that correspond exactly (though generally
   without case sensitivity) to the value provided in the search filter.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm><filename>errors</filename> log</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Directory server log tracing server events, error conditions, and
   warnings, categorized and identified by severity.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Export</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Save directory data in an LDIF file.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Extended operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Additional LDAP operation not included in the original standards.
   OpenDJ supports several standard LDAP extended operations.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="extensible-match-index">
  <glossterm>Extensible match index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Index for a matching rule other than approximate, equality, ordering,
   presence, substring or VLV, such as an index for generalized time.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>External user</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An individual that accesses company resources or services but is not
   working for the company. Typically a customer or partner.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="filter">
  <glossterm>Filter</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An LDAP search filter is an expression that the server uses to find
   entries that match a search request, such as
   <literal>(mail=*@example.com)</literal> to match all entries having an
   email address in the example.com domain.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Group</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Entry identifying a set of members whose entries are also in the
   directory.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Idle time limit</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Defines how long OpenDJ allows idle connections to remain open.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Import</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Read in and index directory data from an LDIF file.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Inactive user</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An entry in the directory that once represented a user but which is
   now no longer able to be authenticated.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Directory server backend feature to allow quick lookup of entries
   based on their attribute values.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="approximate-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="equality-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="extensible-match-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="ordering-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="presence-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="substring-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="vlv-index" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="index-entry-limit" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="index-entry-limit">
  <glossterm>Index entry limit</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>When the number of entries that an index key points to exceeds the
   index entry limit, OpenDJ stops maintaining the list of entries for that
   index key.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Internal user</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An individual who works within the company either as an employee or as
   a contractor.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Standard, portable, text-based representation of directory content.
   See <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2849"
   xlink:show="new">RFC 2849</link>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>LDAP URL</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP Uniform Resource Locator such as <literal
   >ldap://directory.example.com:389/dc=example,dc=com??sub?(uid=bjensen)</literal>.
   See <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2255"
   xlink:show="new">RFC 2255</link>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>LDAPS</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP over SSL.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Lightweight Directory Access Protocol (LDAP)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A simple and standardized network protocol used by applications to
   connect to a directory, search for objects and add, edit or remove
   objects. See <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc4510"
   xlink:show="new">RFC 4510</link>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Lookthrough limit</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Defines the maximum number of candidate entries OpenDJ considers when
   processing a search.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Matching rule</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Defines rules for performing matching operations against assertion
   values. Matching rules are frequently associated with an attribute syntax
   and are used to compare values according to that syntax. For example, the
   <literal>distinguishedNameEqualityMatch</literal> matching rule can be used
   to determine whether two DNs are equal and can ignore unnecessary spaces
   around commas and equal signs, differences in capitalization in attribute
   names, and so on.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Modify DN operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP modification operation to request that the server change the
   distinguished name of an entry.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Modify operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP modification operation to request that the server change one or
   more attributes of an entry.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Naming context</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Base DN under which client applications can look for user data.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Object class</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Identifies entries that share certain characteristics. Most commonly,
   an entry's object classes define the attributes that must and may be present
   on the entry. Object classes are stored on entries as values of the
   <literal>objectClass</literal> attribute. Object classes are defined in the
   directory schema, and can be abstract (defining characteristics for other
   object classes to inherit), structural (defining the basic structure of an
   entry, one structural inheritance per entry), or auxiliary (for decorating
   entries already having a structural object class with other required and
   optional attributes).</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Object identifier (OID)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>String that uniquely identifies an object, such as
   <literal>0.9.2342.19200300.100.1.1</literal> for the user ID attribute or
   <literal>1.3.6.1.4.1.1466.115.121.1.15</literal> for
   <literal>DirectoryString</literal> syntax. </para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Operational attribute</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An attribute that has a special (operational) meaning for the
   directory server, such as <literal>pwdPolicySubentry</literal> or
   <literal>modifyTimestamp</literal>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="ordering-index">
  <glossterm>Ordering index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Index used to match values for a filter that specifies a range.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Password policy</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A set of rules regarding what sequence of characters constitutes an 
   acceptable password. Acceptable passwords are generally those that would be
   too difficult for another user or an automated program to guess and thereby
   defeat the password mechanism. Password policies may require a minimum
   length, a mixture of different types of characters (lowercase, uppercase,
   digits, punctuation marks, and so forth), avoiding dictionary words or
   passwords based on the user's name, and so forth. Password policies may
   also require that users not reuse old passwords and that users change their
   passwords regularly.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Password reset</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Password change performed by a user other than the user who owns the
   entry.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Password storage scheme</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Mechanism for encoding user passwords stored on directory entries.
   OpenDJ implements a number of password storage schemes.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Password validator</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Mechanism for determining whether a proposed password is acceptable
   for use. OpenDJ implements a number of password validators.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="presence-index">
  <glossterm>Presence index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Index used to match the fact that an attribute is present on the entry,
   regardless of the value.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Principal</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Entity that can be authenticated, such as a user, a device, or an
   application.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="privilege">
  <glossterm>Privilege</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Server configuration settings controlling access to administrative
   operations such as exporting and importing data, restarting the server,
   performing password reset, and changing the server configuration.</para>
   <para>Privileges are implemented independently from access control
   instructions (ACI), which apply to LDAP operations and user data.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="access-control-instruction" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Referential integrity</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Ensuring that group membership remains consistent following changes
   to member entries.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm><filename>referint</filename> log</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Directory server log tracing referential integrity events, with
   entries similar to the errors log.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Referral</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Reference to another directory location, which can be another
   directory server running elsewhere or another container on the same server,
   where the current operation can be processed.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Relative distinguished name (RDN)</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Initial portion of a DN that distinguishes the entry from all other
   entries at the same level, such as <literal>uid=bjensen</literal> in
   <literal>uid=bjensen,ou=People,dc=example,dc=com</literal>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="replication">
  <glossterm>Replication</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Data synchronization that ensures all directory servers participating
   eventually share a consistent set of directory data.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm><filename>replication</filename> log</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Directory server log tracing replication events, with entries similar
   to the errors log.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="root-dn">
  <glossterm>Root DN</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A directory superuser, whose account is specific to a directory server
   under <literal>cn=Root DNs,cn=config</literal>.</para>
   <para>The default Root DN is Directory Manager. You can create additional
   Root DN accounts, each with different administrative privileges.</para>
   <glossseealso otherterm="directory-manager" />
   <glossseealso otherterm="privilege" />
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Root DSE</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>The directory entry with distinguished name "" (empty string), where
   DSE stands for DSA-Specific Entry. DSA stands for Directory Server Agent,
   a single directory server. The root DSE serves to expose information over
   LDAP about what the directory server supports in terms of LDAP controls,
   auth password schemes, SASL mechanisms, LDAP protocol versions, naming
   contexts, features, LDAP extended operations, and so forth.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Schema</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP schema defines the object classes, attributes types, attribute
   value syntaxes, matching rules and so on that constrain entries held by the
   directory server.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Search filter</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>See <xref linkend="filter"/>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Search operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP lookup operation where a client requests that the server return
   entries based on an LDAP filter and a base DN under which to search.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Simple authentication</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Bind operation performed with a user's entry DN and user's password.
   Use simple authentication only if the network connection is secure.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Size limit</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Sets the maximum number of entries returned for a search.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Static group</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Group that enumerates member entries.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Subentry</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An entry, such as a password policy entry, that resides with the user
   data but holds operational data, and is not visible in search results unless
   explicitly requested.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="substring-index">
  <glossterm>Substring index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Index used to match values specified with wildcards in the filter.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Task</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Mechanism to provide remote access to directory server administrative
   functions. OpenDJ supports tasks to backup and restore backends, to import
   and export LDIF files, and to stop and restart the server. </para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Time limit</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Defines the maximum processing time OpenDJ devotes to a search
   operation.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Unbind operation</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>LDAP operation to release resources at the end of a session.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Unindexed search</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Search operation for which no matching index is available. If no
   indexes are applicable, then the directory server potentially has to go
   through all entries to look for candidate matches. For this reason, the
   <literal>unindexed-search</literal> privilege, allowing users to request
   searches for which no applicable index exists, is reserved for the directory
   manager by default.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>User</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An entry that represents an individual that can be authenticated
   through credentials contained or referenced by its attributes. A user may
   represent an internal user or an external user, and may be an active user
   or an inactive user.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>User attribute</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An attribute for storing user data on a directory entry such as
   <literal>mail</literal> or <literal>givenname</literal>.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Virtual attribute</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An attribute with dynamically generated values that appear in entries
   but are not persistently stored in the backend.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Virtual directory</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>An application that exposes a consolidated view of multiple physical
   directories over an LDAP interface. Consumers of the directory information
   connect to the virtual directory's LDAP service. Behind the scenes, requests
   for information and updates to the directory are sent to one or more physical
   directories where the actual information resides. Virtual directories enable
   organizations to create a consolidated view of information that for legal or
   technical reasons cannot be consolidated into a single physical copy.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry xml:id="vlv-index">
  <glossterm>Virtual list view (VLV) index</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>Browsing index designed to help the directory server respond to client
   applications that need for example to browse through a long list of results
   a page at a time in a GUI.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>Virtual static group</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>OpenDJ group that lets applications see dynamic groups as what appear
   to be static groups.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>

 <glossentry>
  <glossterm>X.500</glossterm>
  <glossdef>
   <para>A family of standardized protocols for accessing, browsing and
   maintaining a directory. X.500 is functionally similar to LDAP, but is
   generally considered to be more complex, and has consequently not been
   widely adopted.</para>
  </glossdef>
 </glossentry>
</glossary>
