<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! trunk/opendj3/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-before-you-install'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
         xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Before You Install OpenDJ Software</title>

 <para>This chapter covers requirements to consider before you run OpenDJ,
 especially before you run OpenDJ in your production environment.</para>

 <para>If you have a special request to support a combination not listed here,
 contact ForgeRock at <link xlink:href='mailto:info@forgerock.com'
 >info@forgerock.com</link>.</para>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-java">
  <title>Java Environment</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Java</primary>
   <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  
  <para>OpenDJ software consists of pure Java applications. OpenDJ servers
  and clients therefore should run on any system with full Java support.
  OpenDJ is tested on a variety of operating systems, including Solaris
  SPARC and x86, various Linux distributions, Microsoft Windows,
  and Apple Mac OS X.</para>
  
  <para>OpenDJ software requires Java 6 or 7, specifically at least the Java
  Standard Edition runtime environment. ForgeRock has tested most with Oracle
  Java Platform, Standard Edition.</para>

  <para>ForgeRock recommends that you keep your Java installation up to date
  with the latest security fixes.</para>

  <para>To build applications with the OpenDJ LDAP SDK, you need the
  corresponding Java SDK.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-file-descriptors">
  <title>Maximum Open Files</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>File descriptors</primary>
   <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>OpenDJ needs to be able to open many files, especially when handling
  many client connections. Linux systems in particular often set a limit of
  1024 per user, which is too low for OpenDJ.</para>

  <para>When setting up OpenDJ for production use, make sure OpenDJ can use
  at least use at least 64K (65536) file descriptors. For example when running
  OpenDJ as user <literal>opendj</literal> on a Linux system that uses
  <filename>/etc/security/limits.conf</filename> to set user level limits,
  you can set soft and hard limits by adding these lines to the file.</para>

  <programlisting language="none">opendj soft nofile 65536
opendj hard nofile 131072</programlisting>

  <para>The example above assumes the system has enough file descriptors
  available overall. You can check the Linux system overall maximum as
  follows.</para>

  <screen>$ cat /proc/sys/fs/file-max
204252</screen>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-operating-systems">
  <title>Operating System</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Operating systems</primary>
   <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>OpenDJ software depends on the Java environment more than it depends
  on the underlying operating system. That said, OpenDJ
  <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?> has been validated on the following operating
  systems.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Apple Mac OS X 10.7, 10.8</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Linux 2.6 and later</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Microsoft Windows Server 2008 R2 and Windows Server 2012</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Oracle Solaris 11 x86</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In order to avoid directory database file corruption after crashes or
  power failures on Linux systems, enable file system write barriers and make
  sure that the file system journaling mode is ordered. For details on how to
  enable write barriers and how to set the journaling mode for data, see the
  options for your file system in the <command>mount</command> command manual
  page.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-virtualization">
  <title>Virtualization</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Virtualization</primary>
   <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>ForgeRock has tested OpenDJ software on systems running atop VMware
  vSphere Hypervisor (ESXi) 5.1.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-application-servers">
  <title>Application Servers</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Application servers</primary>
   <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>OpenDJ directory server runs as a standalone Java service, and
  does not depend on an application server.</para>

  <para>OpenDJ DSML gateway has been validated on Apache Tomcat 6 and 7.</para>

  <para>OpenDJ REST LDAP gateway has been validated on Apache Tomcat 6 and
  Jetty 8.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-fqdn">
  <title>FQDNs For Replication</title>

  <indexterm><primary>Fully qualified domain name requirements</primary></indexterm>
  <para>OpenDJ replication requires that you use fully qualified domain names,
  such as <literal>opendj.example.com</literal>.</para>

  <para>Although you can use host names like <literal>my-laptop.local</literal>
  for evaluation, in production and even in your lab, you must either ensure
  DNS is set up correctly to provide fully qualified domain names, or set up
  <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> (or
  <filename>C:\Windows\System32\drivers\etc\hosts</filename>) to provide
  fully qualified domain names.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="prerequisites-hardware">
  <title>Hardware</title>

  <para>Thanks to the underlying Java platform, OpenDJ software runs well
  on a variety of processor architectures. Many directory service
  deployments meet their service-level agreements without the very latest
  or very fastest hardware.</para>

  <indexterm><primary>Memory requirements</primary></indexterm>
  <para>For a server evaluation installation, you need 256 MB memory (32-bit)
  or 1 GB memory (64-bit) available to OpenDJ, with 100 MB free disk space for
  the software and a small set of sample data. For installation in production,
  read the rest of this section. You need at least 2 GB memory for OpenDJ and
  4 times the disk space needed to house initial production data in LDIF
  format.<footnote>
   <para>OpenDJ stores data in Berkeley DB Java Edition, which is implemented
   as a rolling log. Berkeley DB appends updates to the end of the last log
   file, and marks old pages as deleted. Berkeley DB cleaner threads monitor
   the log file occupancy ratio, moving the data to get rid of old log files.
   Yet, with the default occupancy ratio of 50%, log files are cleaned only
   when they have less than 50% valid pages. As a result, the database can
   reach twice its initial size in the worst case.</para>
   <para>Furthermore, when you import data from LDIF, OpenDJ stores not only
   the data, but also builds indexes for many of the attributes, resulting in
   some growth. Replication historical data and other operational attributes
   can also take up space.</para>
   <para>Finally, it makes sense to leave space for growth in the database size
   as you modify and add entries over time.</para></footnote>
  To get a more accurate estimate of the disk space needed, import a known
  fraction of the initial LDIF with OpenDJ configured as for production, run
  tests based on the estimated rates of change and growth in directory data,
  and then use the actual space used in the test environment to estimate how
  much disk space you need in production.</para>

  <para>OpenDJ directory servers almost always benefit from having enough
  system memory to cache all directory database files used. The reason
  is that reading from and writing to memory is typically much faster
  than reading from and writing to disk storage. For small data sets,
  you might not need extra memory. For large directories with millions of
  user directory entries, the system might not have enough slots to house
  sufficient memory to cache everything. To improve performance in such
  cases, one approach is to add solid state drives as an intermediate
  cache between memory and disk storage.</para>

  <para>Processor architectures that provide fast single thread execution
  tend to help OpenDJ software deliver the lowest response times. For top end
  performance in terms both of sub-millisecond response times and also
  of throughput ranging from tens of thousands to hundreds of thousands
  of operations per second, the latest x86/x64 architecture chips tend to
  perform better than others tested. Chip multi-threading (CMT) processors
  can do very well on directory servers providing pure search throughput,
  even though response times can be higher. Yet, CMT processors can be slow
  to absorb hundreds or thousands of write operations per second. Their
  slower threads get blocked waiting on resources, and thus are not optimal
  for topologies with high write throughput requirements.</para>

  <indexterm><primary>Network requirements</primary></indexterm>
  <para>On systems with fast processors and enough memory to cache directory
  data completely, the network can become a bottleneck. Even if a single
  1 Gbit Ethernet interface offers plenty of bandwidth to handle your
  average traffic load, it can be too small for peak traffic loads.
  Furthermore, you might choose to use separate interfaces for
  administrative traffic and application traffic. To estimate what network
  hardware you need, calculate the size of the data you return to
  applications during peak load. For example, if you expect to have a
  peak load of 100,000 searches per second, each returning a full 8 KB
  entry, you need a network that can handle 800 MB/sec (3.2 Gbit/sec)
  throughput, not counting any other operations such as writes that
  result in replication traffic.</para>

  <indexterm><primary>Storage requirements</primary></indexterm>
  <para>The storage hardware you choose must allow you to house not only
  directory data including historical data for replication, but also
  logs. If you choose to retain access logs for auditing purposes on a
  heavily used directory, dedicate storage for the log archives as well.
  Furthermore, your storage must also keep pace with the write
  throughput. Write throughput can arise from modify, modify DN, add,
  and delete operations, but it can also result from bind operations.
  Such is the case when the last successful bind is recorded, and when
  account lockout is configured, for example. In a replicated topology,
  not only does a directory service write entries to disk when they are
  changed, but a directory service also writes changelog data and
  historical information in order to resolve potential replication
  conflicts. You base your network throughput needs on peak loads. Also
  base your storage throughput needs on peak loads.</para>

  <note>
   <para>OpenDJ servers do not currently support network file systems such
   as NFS for database storage. Provide sufficient disk space on local storage
   such as internal disk or an attached disk array.</para>
  </note>
 </section>
</chapter>
