<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! trunk/opendj3/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-issues'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
         xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>OpenDJ Fixes, Limitations, &amp; Known Issues</title>

 <para>This chapter covers the status of key issues and limitations for OpenDJ
 <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?> and OpenDJ SDK <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?>.
 For details and information on other issues, see the <link xlink:show="new"
 xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENDJ" >OpenDJ issue
 tracker</link>.</para>

 <section xml:id="fixes">
  <title>Key Fixes</title>

  <note><!-- TODO: reconsider when 2.4.x is no longer supported. -->
   <para>OpenDJ 2.6.0 includes important improvements to replication.
   Replication remains fully compatible with earlier versions. However, some
   operations that work fine with OpenDJ 2.6.0, such as replicating large
   groups and replicating high volumes of adds and deletes, can cause
   issues for earlier versions. Make sure you upgrade all servers to 2.6.0
   before allowing clients to take advantage of write operations that could
   cause trouble for older servers.</para>
  </note>

  <para>The following important bugs were fixed in this release.</para>

  <para>TODO</para><!-- https://github.com/markcraig/release-notes-list-builder -->
 </section>

 <section xml:id="limitations">
  <title>Limitations</title>

  <para>Release <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?> has the following limitations,
  none of which are new since <?eval ${stableServerVersion}?>.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenDJ directory server provides full LDAP v3 support, except for
    alias dereferencing, and limited support for LDAPv2.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>When you configure account lockout as part of password policy,
    OpenDJ locks an account after the specified number of consecutive
    authentication failures. Account lockout is not transactional across a
    replication topology, however. Global account lockout occurs as soon as
    the authentication failure times have been replicated.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenDJ is not fully integrated with Microsoft Windows, yet OpenDJ
    directory server can be run as a service, and thus displayed in the
    Windows Services Control Panel.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenDJ replication is designed to permit an unlimited number
    of replication servers in your topology. Project testing has, however,
    focused only on topologies of up to eight replication servers.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenDJ plugin extensions must follow the guidelines set forth in
    the <filename>README</filename> file delivered in
    <filename>opendj/example-plugin.zip</filename>. When developing your
    extension, aim to remain loosely coupled with any particular version of
    OpenDJ. Libraries used must be installed in
    <filename>opendj/lib/extensions/</filename> (or bundle them in your
    .jar). Keep your configuration separate from the server configuration.
    Also, unless you are reusing standard schema definitions, keep your
    schema definitions separate as well.</para>

    <para>This can affect how your extension works after upgrade. In
    particular <literal>opendj-accountchange-handler-1.0.0</literal> does
    not work with OpenDJ 2.6.0 after upgrade (<link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENDJ-991"
    >OPENDJ-991</link>). See that issue for notes on how make that version
    of the extension work with OpenDJ 2.6.0.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>On Niagara systems such as T2000, hardware SSL crypto acceleration
    runs more slowly than software crypto acceleration. To work around this
    issue take the following actions.</para>
    <orderedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>Add more request handlers to LDAP (for TLS) and LDAPS (for SSL)
      connection handlers.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>Disable hardware acceleration for server's JVM by removing the
      SunPKCS11 security provider from
      <filename>jre/lib/security/java.security</filename>.</para>
     </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="known-issues">
  <title>Known Issues</title>

  <tip>
   <para>When deploying for production, make sure that you follow the
   installation instructions on allowing OpenDJ to use at least 64K (65536)
   file descriptors, and on tuning the JVM appropriately.</para>
  </tip>

  <para>The following important issues remained open at the time this release
  became available.</para>

  <para>TODO</para><!-- https://github.com/markcraig/release-notes-list-builder -->
 </section>
</chapter>
