<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! trunk/opendj3/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-whats-new'
  xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
  xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
  xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
  xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
  xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
  <title>What's New in OpenDJ <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?></title>

  <para>Compared to the OpenDJ <?eval ${stableServerVersion}?>, OpenDJ
  <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?> fixes a number of issues. OpenDJ
  <?eval ${docTargetVersion}?> provides the following new features.</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now lets you filter access and audit logs to focus on
     messages that interest you. OpenDJ supports many criteria for flexible
     log filtering. (OPENDJ-308)</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now logs use of the proxied authorization V1 control with
     <literal>obsoleteProxiedAuthzV1Control</literal> (OPENDJ-283).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ DSML gateway can now connect over SSL to the LDAP
     server (OPENDJ-269).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>OpenDJ now lets you delegate authentication to another LDAP
      directory service, such as Active Directory. The feature is called
      <firstterm>pass through authentication</firstterm> (PTA) (OPENDJ-262).
      With PTA, OpenDJ replays a user's simple bind operation against the remote
      directory service. If the bind is successful, OpenDJ considers the user
      authenticated to perform subsequent operations like searches and updates
      in OpenDJ.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <para>For PTA to work, OpenDJ must be able to match its OpenDJ entry for
       the user with the user's entry on the remote directory service. The two
       entries must correspond in one of the following ways.</para>
       <listitem>
        <para>Both the OpenDJ entry and the remote entry have the same
        DN.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>The OpenDJ entry has an attribute that holds the DN of the entry
        on the remote directory service.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>The OpenDJ entry and the remote entry share an attribute that
        has exactly the same value.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>If user entries do not match originally, you can no doubt add an
      attribute to users' OpenDJ entries when configuring them to use pass
      through authentication.</para>
      <para>To configure PTA, you set up an LDAP pass through authentication
      policy in OpenDJ's configuration, and then assign the policy to users in
      the same way you would assign a password policy. See the
      <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-pta"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
      ><citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle></link> for details.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now lets you configure attributes to be removed or renamed
     on update (OPENDJ-258).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now calls Account Status Notification Handlers when an
     account in enabled or disabled by the <command>manage-account</command>
     (OPENDJ-248).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now adds <literal>Unindexed</literal> to access log response
     messages for unindexed searches, making it easier to identify searches
     rejected by default (OPENDJ-246).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ can now synchronize Samba password attribute values with the
     <literal>userPassword</literal> attribute value, ensuring that when users
     change their LDAP passwords in OpenDJ or change their LanMan or NT
     passwords in Samba, their password attribute values all stay in sync
     (OPENDJ-233). To activate this feature, configure the OpenDJ Samba
     Password plugin by using the <command>dsconfig</command> command.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now supports checking that entries of new group members
     exist (OPENDJ-221).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now better supports more, and larger static groups
     (OPENDJ-197).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Change log content and configuration has been improved in this
     release (OPENDJ-194).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Default database cache size, request handler counts, and replication
     purge delay are now set more sensibly for default installations
     (OPENDJ-116, OPENDJ-186).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>The character set password validator now supports optional character
     sets (OPENDJ-168).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Collective attributes can now be applied based on the values of
     virtual attributes (OPENDJ-76).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now lets you configure the access log to display LDAP
     controls (OPENDJ-60).</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenDJ now lets you execute control-panel as any user, not only the
     user who installed OpenDJ (OPENDJ-19).</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
