<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-account-lockout'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Implementing Account Lockout</title>
 
 <para>OpenDJ directory server supports automatic account lockout.
 The aim of account lockout is not to punish users who mistype their
 passwords, but instead to protect the directory against attacks
 in which the attacker attempts to guess a user password, repeatedly
 attempting to bind until success is achieved.</para>

 <para>Account lockout disables a user account after a specified
 number of successive bind failures. When you implement account
 lockout, you can opt to have the directory server unlock the account
 again after a specified interval, or you can leave the account locked
 until the password is reset.</para>
 
 <para>The catch is that if an attacker has separate access to each
 directory server replica in a topology, the attacker can try passwords
 until lockout on each server separately, or until replication manages
 to lock the accounts. In the worst case, therefore, the attacker gets
 N x R tries, where N is the number of bind failures allowed on a directory
 server, and R is the number of directory server replicas in the
 topology.</para>
 
 <para>This chapter shows you how to set up account lockout policies,
 and how to intervene manually to lock and unlock accounts.</para>

</chapter>

