<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-attribute-uniqueness'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Implementing Attribute Value Uniqueness</title>

 <para>Some attribute values ought to remain unique. If you are using
 <literal>uid</literal> values as RDNs to distinguish between millions of
 user entries stored under <literal>ou=People</literal>, then you do not
 want your directory too contain two or more identical
 <literal>uid</literal> values. If your credit card or mobile number is
 stored as an attribute value on your directory entry, you certainly do not
 want to share that credit card or mobile number with another customer.
 The same is true for your email address.</para>
 
 <para>The difficulty for you as directory administrator lies in
 implementing attribute value uniqueness without sacrificing the high
 availability that comes from using OpenDJ's loosely consistent,
 multi-master data replication. Indeed OpenDJ's replication model lets
 you maintain write access during network partitions for directory
 applications. Yet, write access during a network partition can result in the
 same, theoretically unique attribute value getting assigned to two different
 entries at once. You do not notice the problem until the network partition
 goes away and replication resumes.</para>
 
 <para>This chapter shows you how to set up attribute value uniqueness
 in your directory environment.</para>

</chapter>

